Guide to the Records of the California Association for Health, Physical Education, Recreation and Dance (CAHPERD), 1957-2011 M2043
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
California Association for Health, Physical Education, Recreation and Dance (CAHPERD) records
1957-2011
M2043
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
6.5 Linear feet (13 manuscript boxes)
Records of the California Association for Health, Physical Education, Recreation and Dance (CAHPERD), a non-profit organization founded in 1930 to promote the organizing and progress of school, community and statewide programs of health, physical education, recreation and dance.
California Association for Health, Physical Education, Recreation and Dance.
Biographical/Historical note
The California Association for Health, Physical Education, Recreation and Dance (CAHPERD), founded in 1930, is a non-profit, voluntary membership corporation formed exclusively to promote the organizing and progress of school, community and statewide programs of health, physical education, recreation and dance which embody such opportunities and which insures the inclusion of such programs within the most appropriate philosophical and social context of life in California.
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Scope and Contents
The materials consist of organizational documents, newsletters, executive committee and executive board minutes going back to 1949. It includes correspondence, calls for action, statements of position on proposed legislation and drafts of legislative action related to Title IX and sports in California public schools. It contains the conference programs, bylaws and constitution of CAHPERD from 1967 onward. There is documentation on the CIF (California Interscholastic Federation) transition that occurred from 1974-1976.
Acquisition Information
Gift of California Association for Health, Physical Education, Recreation and Dance, 2014. Accession 2014-101.
California Association for Health, Physical Education, Recreation and Dance.; California Association for Health, Physical Education, Recreation and Dance.; United States. Education Amendments of 1972. Title IX.; Coaching (Athletics)--Research.; Physical education and training--California.; Physical education for women.; Referees--California.; Referees--United States.; School sports--United States.
- Series 1: California Division of Girls and Women in Sports, 1957-2006
  Scope and Contents
  The materials consist of officer duties and codes, books, surveys, directories, booklets, photos, audio tape, awards, memorabilia, studies, and other material related to the California Division of Girls and Women in Sport. Also included are some California Interscholastic Federation documents.
  - DGWS Operating Code (Folder 1 of 2), 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    The materials consist of officer duties and codes.
  - DGWS Operating Code (Folder 2 of 2), 1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Suggested Format for League Constiution and By-Laws, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 3)
    The materials consist of a book written by Mary Ann Turner, PhD entitled "Suggested Format for League Constitution and By- Laws for Girls' Interscholastic Programs".
  - Girls Participation Survey, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    The materials consist of Girls’ Interscholastic Athletic Participation Survey 1972-73 School Year written by William Russell, State CIF Commissioner.
  - Directories, 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    The materials consist of Girls and Women’s Sports California Sports Directories.
  - Competitive Athletics, September 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    The materials consist of Competitive Athletics Booklet from the US Dept of H, Ed, and Welfare written by Margaret Dunkle.
  - Misc. correspondence, minutes, rosters--GWS, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    The materials consist of misc. correspondence, minutes and rosters from the GWS.
  - Stalled at the Start: Project on Equal Education Rights, November 1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    The materials consist of a booklet entitled Stalled at the Start: Project on Equal Education Rights from Government Action on Sex Bias in the Schools.
  - CIF Constitution and By Laws, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    The materials consist of CIF Constitution and By Laws- Basic Statewide rules.
  - California Women’s Coalition, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    The materials consist of California Women’s Coalition. CAHPERD members involved in GWS were active in numerous women’s rights groups—CWC being one of them.
  - CWCA Board, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    The materials consist of photos of the CWCA Board in 1980. The CWCA was the organization formed to take legal action to force the CIF to implement Title IX.
  - Issues in GWS, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    The materials consist of a tape disucssing issues in GWS presented at the AAHPERD Conference by Chris Shelton.
  - Resolutions and Proclamations, 1988-2003 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    The materials consist of Resolutions & Proclamations re: Girls’ & Women’s sport. Both national (NAGWS) and CAHPERD (California GWS) provided materials for members to be proactive.
  - GWS Advocacy Information/Training, 1991-1998 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    The materials consist of GWS Advocacy Information/Training information.
  - CA GWS Links to Leadership (Folder 1 of 2), 1994 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    The materials consist of information from a three-day event to promote leadership in girls and women in sport. The women involved in planning this event were Patsy Livingston (chair), Libby Anderson, Eleanor Bewley, Cathy Bowyer, Phyllis Lerner, Kathie Maier, Ellen O’Connor, Kathy Davilla.
  - CA GWS Links to Leadership (Folder 2 of 2), 1994 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - GWS Pathfinder Award, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    The materials consist of GWS Pathfinder Award.
  - CIF 25th Anniversary, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    The materials consist of items from CIF's 25th anniversary.
  - History of CIF, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    The materials consist of a book entitled A History of the California Interscholastic Federation.
  - 2002 Longitudinal Study (Box 2, Folder 4)
    The materials consist of Women in Intercollegiate Sport… Update 1977-2002 written by R. Vivian Carpenter and Linda Jean Acosta.
  - GWS History in Caifornia, 1957-2005 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    The materials consist of GWS history memorabilia.
  - 2006 Longitudinal Study (Box 2, Folder 6)
    The materials consist of Women in Intercollegiate Sport… Update 1977-2002 by Carpenter and Acosta.
- Series 2: Evolution of Women's Coaches Academy, 1957-2004
  The materials consist of documents related to the creation of the California Women's Coaches Academy. Includes booklets, CAPHERD operating codes, correspondence, meeting minutes, brochures, directories, newspaper clippings, newsletters, and other textual material. Organizations including the Association for Intercollegiate Athletics for Women, National Association for Girls and Women in Sport, and American Alliance for Health, Physical Education, Recreation, and Dance are represented in the materials.
  - CAPHER Booklet, 1957
    The materials consist of CAHPER booklet entitled “How to organize and promote Your district and unit CAHPER – Membership Campaign”.
  - Original Roles, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    The materials consist of a booklet outlining the roles, purpose and platforms of the California Association or Health, Physical Education and Recreation.
  - Misc. correspondence, 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    The materials consist of misc. correspondence among CAHPER Officers. Note: The “D” for Dance had not yet been added to the name of the organization.
  - Operating Codes (Folder 1 of 3), 1968 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    The materials consist of operating codes - CAHPERD.
  - Operating Codes (Folder 2 of 3), 1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Operating Codes (Folder 3 of 3), 1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Southern Section annual conference, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    The materials consist of History of Girls’s and Women’s Sports Californa South 1939-1969.
  - Code of Ethics, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    The materials consist of a Code of Ethics booklet. This booklet was prepared by the Southern California Committee for Girls’ and Women’s Sports, a sub-division of CAHPERD.
  - Guidelines for Interscholastic athletic programs for High School girls, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    The materials consist of booklet entitled Guidelines for Interscholastic athletic programs for High School girls.
  - Meeting Minutes, 1972-1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    The materials consist of CIAW & AIAW; NAGWS; CA Girls and Women in Sport-Meeting Minutes. Misc. meeting minutes of state and national organizations concerned with girls’ and women’s’ sports.
  - California Women Coaches Academy Newsletters, 1974-1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    The materials consist of CWCA Newsletters. This is the organization that “grew” out of CAHPERD when CAHPERD President Ash Hayes told CA-GWS leaders they could not sue CIF in the name of CAHPERD.
  - AIAW/NAGWS Newsletters, 1974-1977 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    The materials consist of AIAW/NAGWS newsletters. When AIAW was formed, NAGWS took a “back seat” as AIAW aspired to govern collegiate sport and NAGWS continued to support girls sport through high school.
  - Misc. correspondence from California Department of Education, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    The materials consist of miscellaneous correspondence from the California Department of Education. John Klumb's letters are included.
  - CIF response to request for liaison with GWS, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    The materials consist of CIF response to request for liaison with GWS. Addressed to Karen Johnson.
  - Constitution of California Women Coaches Academy, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    The materials consist of Constitution of California Women Coaches Academy.
  - Coaches' clinic brochures, 1975, 1976, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    The materials consist of three brochures. One is from the 1975 1st Annual California Coaches Clinic. Another is from National GWS National Coaches Conference held in 1978. The third is from Ist Annual National Women’s Coaches Clinic in 1976.
  - CWCA Meeting minutes, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    The materials consist of CWCA meeting minutes.
  - Misc. correspondence & position statements, 1974-1978 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    The materials consist of misc. correspondence & position statements on GWS and CWCA. Some contributors to this material are National officers, e.g. Judy Holland and Carol Oglesby.
  - GWS National Directory, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    The materials consist of GWS National Directory.
  - Commission on Collegiate Athletics, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    The materials consist of Commission on Collegiate Athletics by the American Council on Education.
  - Legal action against CIF (Folder 1 of 3), 1979 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    The materials consist of lead-up to legal action against CIF.
  - Legal action against CIF (Folder 2 of 3), 1979 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    The materials consist of lead up to legal action agsinst CIF.
  - Legal action against CIF (Folder 3 of 3), 1979 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    The materials consist of lead up to legal action against CIF.
  - California Women Coaches Academy (CWCA) emergence (Folder 1 of 2), 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    The materials consist of miscellaneous correspondence, meeting minutes, etc. re: CWCA and its purpose/activities.
  - California Women Coaches Academy (CWCA) emergence (Folder 2 of 2), 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Directory--California Girls and Women in Sport, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    The materials consist of a directory of members, state-wide who were involved in GWS in California.
  - National Level – GWS & AIAW (Folder 1 of 2), 1980-1982 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    The materials consist of a notebook with professional articles, newsletters and correspondence.
  - National Level – GWS & AIAW (Folder 2 of 2), 1980-1982 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Riles Athletic Study Commission, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    The materials consist of newspaper clippings.
  - AAHPERD Conventions (Folder 1 of 2), 1989-1997 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    The materials consist of awards presented at the NAGWS Recognition Awards Programs.
  - AAHPERD Conventions (Folder 2 of 2), 1989-1997 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - CA-GWS Leaders 1959-1982 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    The materials consist of a list of leaders written by Sue Lemaire.
  - NAGWS newsletters, 1991-2003 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    The materials consist of NAGWS newsletters. Once the NCAA took over women’s intercollegiate competition, AIAW merged with them and left NAGWS on their own.
  - Women in Sport and Physical Activity Journal, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    The materials consist of Women in Sport and Physical Activity Journal Vol 13, No. 1.
- Series 3: General documents and photos- CAHPERD activities, 1960-2011
  The materials consist of documents related to the general operations of CAHPERD, including operating codes, constitutions, bylaws, articles, manuals, photos, long-terms plans and vision documents, microfilm journals from the 1970s, and other materials. The activities of CAHPERD's School Health, Athletics, Recreation, and Physical Education Public Affairs Committee are also documented in this series.
  - Constitution, bylaws, articles of incorporation (Folder 1 of 2), 1960-1976 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    The materials consist of CAHPER's constitution, by-laws, articles of incorporation, changes, platfroms, roles and purposes.
  - Constitution, bylaws, articles of incorporation (Folder 2 of 2), 1960-1976 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - CAHPERD Leaders Manual, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    The materials consist of a manual that was used in one of the early leadership trainings.
  - Misc. documents, 1965-1974 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    The materials consist of misc. documents pertaining to incorporation of CAHPERD.
  - Collection of Operating Codes (Folder 1 of 2), 1968 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    The materials consist of a collection of operating codes.
  - Collection of Operating Codes (Folder 2 of 2), 1968 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - GWS Operating Codes, 1969, 1970, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    The materials consist of operating codes for Division of GWS. This shows the evolution of the division and it's scope of work
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    The materials consist of a letter to US Dept. of Educ. Re: implementation of Title IX.
  - Creation and activities of SHARRPE-PAC, 1974-1975 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    The materials consist of activities of CAHPERD's School Health, Athletics, Recreation, and Physical Education Public Affairs Committee.
  - Miscellaneous documents, 1974-1980 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    The materials consist of documents, minutes, etc.
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1974-1988 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    The materials consist of miscellaneous correspondence.
  - State conference Scrapbook, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    The materials consist of a scrapbook report of historian, L.A. Johnson.
  - BOD/Executive Committee Meeting minutes, 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    The materials consist of meeting minutes.
  - CAHPERD PR Training Packet, 1980s (Box 6, Folder 1)
    The materials consist of a booklet for PR training purposes.
  - Misc. Photos Folder 1, 1980-1990 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    The materials consist of miscellaneous photographs.
  - Misc. Photos Folder 2, 1980-1990 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Misc. Photos Folder 3, 1980-1990 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    The materials consist of miscellaneous photographs from CAHPERD envelope.
  - Misc. Photos Folder 4, 1980-1990 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Health classes, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    The materials consist of a consolidation of schools offering Health Education classes.
  - Minutes and actions, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    The materials consist of BOD/EC & Rep Assembly Meeting Minutes.
  - Proposed Resolution to State Board of Education, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    The materials consist of a proposed resolution from a California Board of Education meeting.
  - Photographs, 1988-1989, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    The materials consist of photos from a state conference.
  - Photographs, 1988-1995 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    The materials consist of photographs from new leaders' training, conferences 1988-1995, Legislative Fitness Day 1980's, etc.
  - Photographs, 1988-1989, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    The materials consist of misc. state conference photos.
  - CAHPERD Conference photographs, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    The materials consist of photos from a CAHPERD conference.
  - Southwest District AAHPERD, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    The materials consist of photographs of Bobbie Masters passing gavel to Robert Pestolesi—President elect.
  - CAHPERD's response to waiver requests, 1992-1993 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    The materials consist of letters & press clippings of the defense of physical education.
  - Constitution Bylaws & Articles of Incorporation, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    The materials consist of a booklet of Constitution Bylaws & Articles of Incorporation.
  - CAHPERD Long Range Plan 2003-2006, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    The materials consist of a booklet for long range planning.
  - Board of Directors meeting minutes, 2003, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    The materials consist of meeting minutes from the Board of Directors.
  - Supt. of Education correspondence, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    The materials consist of a letter from Supt. Of Public Education to Jack O'Connell to Pres. Mary Blackman regarding establishing and funding physical education standards of instruction.
  - National Adapted Physical Education Conference, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    The materials consist of photographs from the National Adapted Physical Education Conference.
  - Constitution, Bylaws & Articles of Incorporation, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    The materials consist of a booklet of Constitution, Bylaws & Articles of Incorporation.
  - CAHPERD's Vision for GWS, 2011 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    The materials consist of CAHPERD's 5 year goals for GWS.
  - Calif. Dept. of Justice Women's Rights Handbook (Box 6, Folder 21)
    The materials consist of information pamphlet No. 9. It is not related to GWS or Title IX but CAHPERD thought it was important to have.
  - CAHPERD Journals, 1972-1978 (Box 7)
    The materials consist of three journals on microfilm: CAHPERD Journal, v. 35, 1-5 dated Sept. 1972-June 1973, CAHPERD Journal, v. 36, 1-5 dated Sept. 1973-June 1974 and CAHPERD Journal, v. 40, 1-4 dated Nov. 1977-May 1978.
- Series 4: Riles Commission and CWCA lawsuit vs. CIF, 1973-1991
  Textual materials related to the lawsuit the California Women's Coaches Academy filed against the California Interscholastic Federation in the late 1970s. The CWCA sued the CIF for bias against women in sports, claiming women's game officials were being paid less than the men's, women were refused jobs on the CIF governing board, and fewer girls sports programs were offered than boys sports programs. The suit was settled out of court in 1980. Court documents, minutes, notes, and agendas are included, as well as a several folders of materials from the Riles Commission subcommittee.
  - Formation of Athletic Study Committee, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    The materials consist of the formation of the Athletic Study Committee to study CIF relationships to Girl Forms. It is also called the Riles Commission after Wilson Riles.
  - Colorado Women's Coaches Association (CWCA), 1973-1976 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    The materials consist of minutes, letters and agendas from CWCA.
  - CIF vs CWCA: Complaint documents, 1977-1979 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    The materials consist of complaint documents.
  - CIF vs CWCA: Original filings, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    The materials consist of interrogatories from the lawsuit between CWCA and CIF.
  - CWCA documents, 1977-1979 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    The materials consist of minutes, agendas and letters.
  - State Guidelines for School Athletic Programs, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    The materials consist of a booklet entitled State Guidelines for School Athletic Programs.
  - CIF vs CWCA: lawsuit documents, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    The materials consist of lawsuit documents.
  - Riles Commission sub-committee meeting, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    The materials consist of sub- committee meeting reports, meetings and agendas.
  - Riles Commission committee discussions, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    The materials consist of sub-committee or whole committee with discussions.
  - Riles Commission sub-committee reports, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    The materials consist of sub-committee reports.
  - Riles Commission final report and recommendations, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    The materials consist of final report and recommendations from Ca State Department of Education Athletics Study Committee.
  - Federal Court filing, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    The materials consist of a complaint filed in federal court in the Central District of California. The file which was made with the United States District Court contains a stipulation for settlement.
  - Introduction of SB19, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    The materials consist of a bill to delete the provision giving the department of education general control over athletic activities in the public schools. This was CIF's reaction to pending report from Riles Commission in order to take oversight away from Department of Education to provide CIF complete autonomy.
  - Coach complaints to OCR and EEOC, 1982-1983 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    The materials consist of the L.A. section of coach complaints.
  - CWCA Membership List, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    The materials consist of a membership list.
  - CA Title V, 1990-1991 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    The materials consist of notes, minutes and agendas.
- Series 5: Title IX materials, ca. 1970-2006
  Textual materials related to Title IX, consisting primarily of books, articles, booklets, reports, studies, and other materials for reference.
  - Gender equality miscellaneous, 1970s-1990s (Box 9, Folder 3)
    The materials consist of miscellaneous materials on gender equality.
  - Title IX cases and reports, 1970s-1990s (Box 9, Folder 4)
    The materials consist of miscellaneous cases and reports.
  - Title IX updates and correspondence, 1970s-1990s (Box 9, Folder 5)
    The materials consist of miscellaneous updates and correspondence.
  - Project on the Status and Education of Women, September 1975 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    The materials consist of a project entitled "What constitutes equality for Women in Sport?". The writers include B. Sandler, M, Dunkle, F., Gleaves, K., Meckes, and L. Hunter. Leaders in girls’/women’s sport collected information from all sources to build their cases for equity in their domain.
  - Sex Discrimination Against Students: Implications of Title IX of the Education Amendments of 1972, November 1975 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    The materials consist of a pamphlet written by Margaret C. Dunkle and Bernice Sandler.
  - Complying with Title IX, Implementing Institutional Self-Evaluation, 1976 [?] (Box 10, Folder 1)
    The materials consist of a booklet produced by the US Dept. of Health, Education and Welfare and Office of Education.
  - Conference on the Status of Girls’ Athletic Programs in Ca Public Schools, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    The materials consist of a booklet produced by Larry Harrington, Coordinator, CDE.
  - Title IX The Unenforced Law, January 1978 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    The materials consist of a booklet entitled "Title IX The Unenforced Law: Title IX Activity by Federal Agencies other than HEW" produced by the Report of the National Advisory Council on Women’s Educational Programs.
  - Title IX Questions, Answers and Comments, May 1978 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    The materials consist of a booklet produced by Assessment Office at the Los Angeles Unified School District.